<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Twelve humble proposals to the supreme governours of the three nations now assembled at Westminster, concerning the propogation of the gospel, new modling of the Universities, reformation of the laws, supply of the necessities of the poor and many other things of great moment, which may conduce to the honour of God, and the comfort and joy of his people. By M.R. an admirer and adorer of the good providence of God, in making such happy changes in these nations.</title>
            <author>M. R.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92239</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R51</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R230141</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895924</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895924</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153509</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92239)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153509)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2368:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Twelve humble proposals to the supreme governours of the three nations now assembled at Westminster, concerning the propogation of the gospel, new modling of the Universities, reformation of the laws, supply of the necessities of the poor and many other things of great moment, which may conduce to the honour of God, and the comfort and joy of his people. By M.R. an admirer and adorer of the good providence of God, in making such happy changes in these nations.</title>
                  <author>M. R.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Henry Hills, for R.C. and are to be sold by Giles Calvert, at the Black-spread Eagle, at the west-end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The words "propogation ... of the poor" are gathered in a left brace.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library, Washington, D.C..</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Law reform --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Poor --  Services for --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Universities and colleges --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153509:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TWELVE HUMBLE PROPOSALS To the Supreme Governours of the three Nations now aſſembled at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> concerning The
<list>
                  <item>Propogation of the Goſpel,</item>
                  <item>New modling of the Univerſities,</item>
                  <item>Reformation of the Laws.</item>
                  <item>ſupply of the neceſſities of the poor;</item>
               </list>
And many other things of great moment, which may conduce to the honour of God, and the comfort and joy of his people.</p>
            <p>By <hi>M. R.</hi> an admirer and adorer of the good provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God, in making ſuch happy changes in theſe Nations.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 29.2.</hi>
               </bibl> When the righteous are in authority the people rejoice, but when the wicked beareth Rule, the people mourn.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Judges 5.9.</hi>
               </bibl> My heart is toward the Governours of Iſrael, who offered them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves willingly among the people.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 28.16.</hi>
               </bibl> The Prince that wanteth underſtanding is a great oppreſſor, but he that hateth covetouſneſſe ſhall prolong his dayes, <hi>Prov. 22.16.</hi> He that oppreſſeth the poor to increaſe his riches, and he that giveth to the rich ſhall ſurely come to want.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Henry Hills,</hi> for <hi>R. C.</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> at the <hi>Black-ſpread Eagle,</hi> at the Weſt-end of <hi>Pauls</hi> 1653.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:153509:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:153509:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable the Supreme Governours of the three Nations now aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled at <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I read and conſider thoſe ſacred Chronicles of the Kings and Governours of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael,</hi> how variouſly they acted in their ſeveral affairs towards God and man; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times finding that the Kings and Governours of thoſe times were not upright with God, but turn'd aſide from him, and conſequently, they were of profane and carnall hearts, and then the worſhip of God was laid aſide, and Idols were ſet up, and their actions were profane and unjuſt, and every one loved covetouſneſſe, and none called for juſtice; And ſometimes again, finding as it were the tide turned, and a good <hi>Joaſh,</hi> ſucceding a wicked <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haziah,</hi> and <hi>Athaliah,</hi> and a good <hi>Joſiah</hi> ſucceeding the moſt wicked reign of <hi>Manoſſeth,</hi> and then a moſt bleſſed and glorious change is made in the Nation, and O how greatly is the Lord honoured by ſuch Governours? and how are the hearts of his people made glad? and how doth Juſtice and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe flouriſh? and the Nation in General, fare the better? I ſay, when I conſider theſe things, and compare them with the preſent proceedings of God towards theſe Nations, in laying aſide the late Tyrannicall King that reigned over them, and putting the Government into the hand of a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, among whom there were many good men, (though too many bad al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo) who brought in a bleſſed change, (though not ſuch a reformation as was expected) and gave free liberty to the people of God, to worſhip God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his will, and protected them from the oppoſitions and malice of forein enemies (though not from the oppreſſions of ſome inteſtine inmates, I mean the Lawyers, and wicked men that oppreſſed by the Law;) And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider withall, how God hath removed that mixed Parliament, and convened together a company of men, of whom it is to be hoped, that every individu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al member of them have their hearts upright with God; I do comfortably hope, and am perſwaded, that God will now grant ſuch daies to theſe three Nations, as they injoy'd in <hi>Iudah</hi> in the daies of <hi>David, Solomon, Aſa, Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaphat, Ioaſh, Hezekiah,</hi> and <hi>Ioſiah;</hi> when Judgement did run down as wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and Righteouſneſſe as a mighty ſtream, and the people were called up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on every where, throughout that Realm to cleave unto the Lord, and to walk in his waies, and Juſtice was duly adminiſtred; I will inſtance but in that good King <hi>Iehoſaphat,</hi> of whom it is ſaid, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.8, 9. that he did ſet Judges in all parts of the land, giving them a charge in theſe words, Take heed what ye do, for ye judge not for man, but for the Lord, who is with you
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:153509:3"/>in Judgement, Wherefore now, let the fear of the Lord be upon you, take heed and do it, for there is no iniquity with the Lord our God, nor reſpect of perſons, nor taking of gifts.</p>
            <p>And having this hope, that things will now be carryed in ſuch a current among you, I am encouraged to preſent unto your Honours, theſe few pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſals; being perſwaded, that all things of this nature will be acceptable unto you, and that you having the Spirit of God in you, which preſſeth after Righteouſneſſe and Holineſſe, all motions tending thereto, will be wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, and alſo uſefull unto you, from whomſoever they come; and as for me, I could not chuſe but communicate thoſe few things, that were upon my heart, by way of propoſal to you; though I ſhould have been glad if others had been more forward, and prevented me herein: for ſo it had been done, I ſhould have been ſatisfied, and I could wiſh, if any others had any other thing upon their Spirits, that may be of publique advantage, that they would all preſent them to your confiderations: for it being done onely by way of propoſal, it can be no way prejudicial, but may be ſeverall wayes advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous, to you: (if your Spirits be humble, as I hope they are, and will not ſlight any thing becauſe it is propounded by another) for if it ſhould be ſo, that the ſame things are propounded to you, upon ſollid and good grounds; which you had in your hearts before to do; or if it ſhould be ſo, that what is, or ſhall be propounded to you by any of Gods people (though a great number ſhould make propoſals to you) ſhould come ſhort of what you have already in your heart to do, the Spirit of God, being powred out upon you, to fit you for Government, as it was upon the ſeventy Elders:</p>
            <p>Yet this advantage you would have by their propoſals, that you would be incouraged, to go on vigorouſly in the doing of thoſe things, which both God and his people do perſwade you to.</p>
            <p>And thus leaving you to the conſideration of the following Propoſals, I on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſire you (if there be any thing herein that ſuits not with your inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or intentions) to remember they are but Propoſals: and may be either waved or improved as the Lord ſhall guide your hearts.</p>
            <p>The firſt four propoſals ſhall be concerning General, and the reſt concerning particular things.</p>
            <p>The firſt Propoſal</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Propoſal. That the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours alwaies would reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat Rule over men muſt be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſt, Ruling in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he fear of God.</note>And the firſt thing that I do propound to you in general is, that you la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to keep alwaies freſh upon your Spirits, thoſe laſt words of <hi>David,</hi> the Son of <hi>Ieſſe,</hi> the man who was raiſed up on high, the annointed of the God of <hi>Iacob,</hi> and the ſweet Pſalmiſt of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> mentioned 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.1.2.3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Spirit of the Lord ſpake by me, and his word was in my tongue, the God of Iſrael ſaid, the rock of Iſrael ſpake to me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>He that ruleth over men muſt be juſt, ruling in the fear of God: and he ſhall be as the light of the morning, when the ſun riſeth; even a morning without clouds; as the tender graſs ſpringing out of the earth by clear ſhining after rain.</hi> Wherein ye that are called to be Rulers over men, have your great duty, and your very great incouragement thereunto laid down; your duty being to be juſt, and to Rule in the fear of God, which I hope you will ſeriouſly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der dayly; for your incouragement thereunto is exceeding great, for if you ſo be and do, you ſhall never be put out in obſcurity, not but your light
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:153509:3"/>ſhall be glorious: and the fruits that you bring forth in that light ſhall be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, for you ſhall not be unfruitful, (if you be juſt, and Rule in the fear of God) but you ſhall be as the tender graſs, ſpringing out of the earth by clear ſhining after rain, which is exceeding deſireable to all whom lt concerns. Oh therefore let this pretious word be alwayes ſounding in your ears, and make deep impreſſions in your hearts! HE THAT RULETH OVER MEN, MUST BE JUST, RULING IN THE FEAR OF GOD.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">2. Propoſal. That they would alwaies remember that Jeſus Chriſt muſt now reign, &amp; ſo act as thoſe that are offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers deputed by him.</note>2. Prop. That you would conſider, that the time of the reign of Chriſt is at hand; either perſonally, or by the glorious powrings out of his Spirit upon his people, which will as viſibly demonſtrate that he is King and reigneth, as if he were perſonally on earth, and when he reigneth, he will Judge the world with equity, and the people with his truth. Oh therefore do you ſtrive to be his forerunners! and to give the world a taſt, what it is to have Jeſus Chriſt to reign over the Nations of the earth (either immediately in his own perſon, or mediately by his Saints, making them Princes in all Lands) by doing ſuch Juſt and Righteous things, as you do know, or may know, Jeſus Chriſt will do when he reigns on earth; ſo will you do as much as in you lieth to ſet up the Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt on earth, and to haſten that glorious time for which the Spirit, and the Bride, the Spouſe of Jeſus Chriſt hath ſo long waited, Saying, <hi>come Lord Ieſus, come quickly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Prop. that you would take up holy reſolutions in the ſtrength of the Lord, <note>PLACE="marg" 3. Prop. That they would make it all their care to do ſervice for Chriſt in their place, and leave the care of themſelves, and their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to him.</note> and not your own ſtrength, to lay aſide all your own intereſts, and outward advantages, and to be in a manner careleſs of your own outward e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, not caring what becomes of them, ſo you may advance Chriſt: but reſolving with a holy indignation to trample upon any worldly advantages, when they come in competition with doing ſervice for Chriſt, not taking care to lay up great eſtates for your poſterity, or to gain great eſtates for your ſelves, aiming at being accounted great and honourable among men (leave you that to others that believe not, <hi>for how can you believe that ſeek honour one of another</hi>) but knowing that the more careleſs you are of providing e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates for your children, and of ſeeking the honour of men; upon the account of doing ſervice for, and the honouring of God, whoſe great name you have taken upon you, and whoſe ſervants you profeſſe your ſelves to be, the more care will God take for you, and yours, and the more honour ſhall ye receive from men, ſaid I from men onely? I might ſay from God alſo, for they that honour God, God will honour. Oh thereſore make it your work to honour God! and truſt him for eſtates, <note>PLACE="marg" 4. Propoſal. That they would be ſpeedy in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the work of Chriſt <hi>made haſt an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> delayed not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> keep thy righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous judge ments.</hi> Pſ. 11<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and whatſoever ſhall be good for you and yours.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Prop. That you be quick and ſpeedy in doing the work of the Lord, being diligent in buſineſs, fervent in Spirit, ſerving the Lord. I ſay be ſpeedy (though not without ſeriouſneſs and conſideration) for hope deferred maketh the heart ſick, and the tedious delays of your predeceſſours in au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, made the Common-wealth ſick and weary, and (with reverence be it ſpoken) God himſelf weary to the ſpuing them out; They ſpending com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly but ſixteen hours in a week, for the diſphatching of thoſe great and weighty things which God called for at their hands, and which they had no
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:153509:4"/>heart unto, whereas they had more need to have ſitten 16. hours in a day, to have diſpatched their work, that ſo there might have been no complainings in our ſtreets. But they accounted onely three or four houres ſitting in the forenoon, onely of four dayes in the week, ſufficient for the doing the work they had to do; as if there were nothing now to be done, but to ſpin out the time of a perpetuall Parliament from age to age, and therefore they would do but a little now, and a little then, conſider of an Act for the relief of the poor, or for paying publique faith-money one day, and then lay it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide for three, ſix, twelve moneths together, and do no more in it this year, than they did the laſt. But oh that by how much they have been negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and careleſs of doing the work which they ought to have done, by ſomuch the more you would be diligent and reſolved, and unwearied in your work, and labour of love for God, and for his people, and for the Common-wealth of the three Nations! I ſay not this as if things could be all done in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for they will deſerve to be blamed that ſhall be too preſſing upon you, and be by and by offended if you make not ſuch haſt as ſome haſty Spirits may expect. But I only propound, that you take up reſolutions to be ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and if you ſo reſolve, and indeavour it, as you can approve your hearts in the ſight of God, you need not care though ſome troubled and haſty Spirits ſhould be offended, only impute it to their zeal and ignorance: And their zeal being good, therefore diſpiſe them not, becauſe of their ignorance of the greatneſs of your work, and the obſtructions that may poſſibly be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in your way.</p>
            <p>And thus much for the general Propoſals, and now I come to propound ſome particular work, which may tend very much to the honour of God, and the joy of his people being done by you.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <note place="margin">5. Propoſal. That they would zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagate the Goſpel.</note> 5. Prop. That it be your earneſt endeavour to propagate the Goſpel; and this I propoſe to you not ſo much as you are Magiſtrates, but as you are Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, that is to ſay, as you have received Chriſt Jeſus the Lord, and ſo are become indeed the Sonnes of God: for it is the duty of every ſuch ſoul as is indeed not onely a Profeſſor, but a Poſſeſſor of Chriſt, to do all that in him lies in his particular place and Station to propagate the Goſpel theſe four ways. Firſt, in praying that the Goſpel may run and be glorified. 2. In im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving what talents he hath for publiſhing the Goſpel; for no man ought to hide his Talent or Talents, but to improve them for his Maſters advantage. 3. In exhorting others whom he finds to be gifted, and fitted to that work, (if he ſee them to neglect it) to improve their Talents for the honour of their Lord. 4. In adminiſtring to the neceſſities of ſuch as do make it their work to preach the Goſpel, but have not any outward eſtates for the ſupply of themſelves and their families, but what is communicated unto them for that work: for ſuch muſt live of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>And theſe four things Right Honourable, I propound to you, as your du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, not as you are Magiſtrates, as I ſaid before, but as you are Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That you inceſſantly pray to the great Lord of the Harveſt, to ſend forth Labourers into his Harveſt, that ſo the Goſpel may be gloriouſly publiſhed abroad in the world,</p>
            <p n="2">2. That although you are Magiſtrates, and have other great affairs in your
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:153509:4"/>hands, yet remember you are alſo Chriſtians and Saints, and you ought to improve your gifts and Tallents this way alſo to your maſters honour as often as you have opportunity. <hi>David</hi> was a Magiſtrate and a Saint, and he did the work of a Magiſtrate in his place, and the work of a Saint alſo. He ceaſed not to publiſh the glorious truths of God in the great congregation.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That you do not onely ſo your ſelves, but that you exhort and incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage others whom you know to be gifted (but of themſelves are ſhie and back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward) to improve their gifts, and this to do as you are Chriſtians; and you being not onely Chriſtians but Magiſtrates, have a greater advantage in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it than other Chriſtians have: for Firſt, you have power to protect thoſe whom you exhort to this duty from the violence of any enemies, if there be any that ſhould dare to oppoſe them, though it is to be hoped that there are none in theſe three Nations under your Juriſdiction, at leaſt none that will openly ſhew themſelves to be ſuch enemies of Chriſt. And Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, you have power to command that the doors of the publick meeting places be ſet open, and free to all that are known to be godly and faithfull diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the word of Chriſt, whether Presbyterians, or thoſe commonly called Anabaptiſts, or Independents, whereas ſome Presbyterian Miniſters have taken upon them very lately, to keep the doors of ſome publick meeting-places ſhut againſt all but themſelves, or whom they pleaſed, and would not ſuffer godly Miniſters to preach in thoſe places, <note place="margin">8. Particular things nece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to be done in order to the propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the Goſpel.</note> no not at ſuch times as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves did not preach, nor any others for them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That you adminiſter to the neceſſities of ſuch as out of love to Chriſt do feed the Lambs and Sheep of Chriſt, with wholeſome food, and make it their work ſo to do, not having any outward eſtate for the ſupply of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their families, but what is adminiſtred unto them for that work; and this likewiſe you may do as you are not onely Chriſtians but Magiſtrates, with a far greater advantage than other Chriſtians may. But under this head I have theſe eight particulars to propound unto you.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">1. That tithes be aboliſhed.</note>1. That you reſolve with all poſſible ſpeed to repeal the Law of Tithes, which is a great oppreſſion not onely to the eſtates, but to the conſciences of many good people.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">2. That blind Prieſts may have no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to miſlead poor ſouls.</note>2. That idle droans that have no acquaintance with Jeſus Chriſt, and know onely how to fleeze and not how to feed the Sheep of Chriſt, may receive no incouragement from you in that work; but rather you ſhould incourage them to leave that work, by inviting of them to ſome other imployment if you think that any of them may be fit for it. But if other private men that are like unto themſelves will ſupport them, or maintain them they may, but they ſhould have no incouragement from you in that work.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">3. That the Paſtors and gifted bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of all the Churches of Chriſt in the Nation be deſired to preach in publick meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing places.</note>3. That ſuch Preachers of the Goſpel as are Paſtors of particular Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations baptized or others, be deſired by you to bring their people into each publick meeting place that is moſt commodious for ſuch a congregation, and neereſt their habitations, both in the City and Country, that ſo the people of that pariſh, and as many as ſhall deſire to hear the word there, may be made partakers of it freely without any charge. The Church in the primitive times did meet in ſuch places where unbelievers might come to hear them, and by that means be convinced of them all, and converted to the faith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.24.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:153509:5"/>4. That in the City of <hi>London,</hi> two or three pariſhes that have but few people belonging to them,<note place="margin">4. That two or three Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to one 5. That god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther godly Preachers may have free liberty alike to preach.</note> may be reduced to one, that ſo there may be ſo much the leſſe charge required for the maintenance of Goſpel preachers, whereas now one man takes a maintenance from a Pariſh, where ſcarce 40. or 50. uſually come to hear him.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That no Miniſter, Presbyterian or other, that is of a Godly converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, be taken from any people that do love and deſire his Miniſtery, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it be to remove only to the diſtance of two or three Pariſhes at moſt, ſo as the people that are affected with his Miniſtery, may hear him if they pleaſe: provided that at other times when he doth not preach, the ſame pulpit may be free for any other godly man to preach there: for there may be other Godly people of the ſame pariſh, or Corporation, that may as much deſire the Miniſtery of another, as they of him, and when it is ſo, the one miniſter ſhould have liberty in the fore-noon, and the other in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon, and ſo both parties may be ſatisfyed.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <note place="margin">6. That ſuch a are Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, and all others that are gifted, and of holy and godly conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations, be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to Preach.</note>6. That for the ſupply of the peoples wants of ſome to diſpence the word unto them, you do not only deſire Paſtors of Churches to preach the word in publick places, but you do alſo deſire thoſe great men, and good men that have great eſtates, that have been ſhy of going into the Pulpits hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to (though they are better furniſhed with gifts, and fitted with abilities; for that work than many that call themſelves miniſters and Clergy men) to go and preach the Goſpell freely, according to thoſe Talents they have received; for it is their duty to do ſo, and as they are the Servants of Chriſt (as every one hathreceived a gift, ſo he ought to miniſter, as good Stewards of the manifold grace of God) they ought to improve their Talents, and in im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving they may increaſe them. And being ſenſible of the great blindneſs people are in for want of teachers, you ought to incourage and invite them thereunto, and for this you have the example of that good King <hi>Iehoſhaphat</hi> 2 <hi>Chron</hi> 17.7, 8. <hi>Who in the third year of his reign ſent to his Princes, even to Benhaill, and to Obadiah, and to Zachariah, and to Nethaneel, and to Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaiah, to teach in the Cities of Iudah, and with them Levites, even Shema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iah, and Nethaniah,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and they taught in Judah, and went throughout all the Cities of Judah, and taught the people.</hi> That good Kings heart being lifted up in the waies of the Lord, ver 6. that is wonderfully inlarged, and raiſed up towards God, he therefore went on in the waies of the Lord vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorouſly, throwing down the falfe prieſts, and falſe worſhip practiſed in thoſe times, and knowing that the generality of the multitude of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were ignorant of the waies of the Lord, He therefore ſent to his Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to go up and down, and teach in the Cities of Judah, not that it may be ſuppoſed that all the Princes of Judah were fit for that work, but he ſent to ſuch of them as he knew to be holy men, and men having the Spirit of the Lord in them, and therefore they are ſingled out, and menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by name even <hi>Benhail, Obadiah, Zechariah, Nethan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>el,</hi> and <hi>Micha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iah,</hi> and with them thoſe Prieſts and Levites alſo that were fitteſt for that work, (for many of the Levites might be as bad as the worſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of others) even ſuch and ſuch by name. Thus do you deſire thoſe that are men of eſtates, whom you know to be gifted as aforeſaid, of whom it may be there may be ten or twelve, or more or leſſe, in a City, or County, to ride abroad in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:153509:5"/>the Country, and improve their gifts among thoſe people <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> want teaching.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <note place="margin">7. That the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſities be new mod'led.</note>7. That (for further ſupply of the people with goſpel Preachers, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or ſupply of maintenance for ſuch as are willing to preach the Goſpel, but have no outward eſtates) the Univerſities be new modelled, And that thoſe eſtates which were intended by the Donors of them to ſuppoſed pious uſes, may be wholly converted to ſuch uſes as are indeed pious, that is to ſay, a part thereof, to be for the ſupply of ſuch Preachers as are able and faithful Miniſters of the New Teſtament, and have not outward eſtates of their own for their ſupply; And another part of thoſe Univerſity eſtates, for the ſupply of ſuch godly Scholars as are to be brought up at the Vniverſities (and their godly Tutors,) and of ſuch of thoſe Scholars onely, as whoſe parents <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re not able to maintain them there themſelves, and that others who deſire to put their children to the Vniverſities, to ſtudy any of the liberal Sciences, do alwaies do it at their own proper charge, and not that things be ſo corruptly carried as they have been, and yet are; That many Scholars that are mens ſons of vaſt eſtates, muſt have fellowſhips (as they now call them) and thoſe that are mean (though their children are godly) cannot have any thing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward their maintenance, if they ſhould ſend them thither; Yea and many of thoſe that they call fellows for love of their fellowſhips, continue in the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities all the dayes of their lives, (ſome of them being ancient gray-headed men) living there an idle life, and never coming abroad to ſet themſelves to any imployment wherein they may be uſefull to Church or Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <note place="margin">8. That ſome ways of main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance out of the publick Treaſury be provided for Goſpel Preachers, but none by way of compulſion from the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</note>8. That beſides the maintenance which may come out of the Univerſity lands, you take care to provide ſome other maintenance for the ſupply of all godly and able Preachers of the Goſpel, whether ſuch as are commonly called Presbyterians, Independents, or others who do attend that work, or ſhall attend that work of Preaching the Goſpel, and have not outward eſtates of their own to live upon: for you have power to imploy the publick trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure for the publick benefit of the Nation, and if for outward benefit, much more for ſpiritual benefit, which you ought in an eſpecial manner to take care of as you are private Chriſtians, and have the better opportunity to do it as you are Magiſtrates.</p>
            <p>But ſtill remember this, that you ought never to preſume to take any more authority upon you to do any thing in the Churches of God, in ordering Church affairs, than you may do as private Chriſtians, wherein you may only adviſe, and deſire things may be ſo and ſo, but may not impoſe any thing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the conſciences of Saints by force, for that were to do as the Beaſt hath done, which I am confidently perſwaded you will never do, nor ſuffer any other under your Juriſdiction to do, by authority from you (though they may deſire it of you.)</p>
            <p>But this let me add further as a caution; that as you take care that tithes be taken away, ſo that by no means you impoſe any law upon the people, to pay ſuch or ſuch a rate, for the maintenance of Miniſters, for of that courſe ſeverall inconveniences will follow, 1. The conſciences of many faithful Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers will ſcruple to take that maintenance of you, which you compel from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who are perſwaded that they ought not to have any thing, but what is
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:153509:6"/>freely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>en, neither directly or indirectly: And 2. The conſciences of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ople do ſcruple to be tied to give ſo much, or ſo much to ſuch a uſe, but are perſwaded that what they give to that uſe, they ought to give freely. 3. Some that are of ſuch particular Churches as meet not in the Pariſh or Town wherein they live (if you ſhould rate people ſeverally) would be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to pay the rate, although they do contribute to their own officers, which will be unreaſonable; for what God makes them willing and able to give of their temporals, they will deſire to give it to thoſe that do adminiſter to them in Spirituals, therefore by no means compell any contributions of this kind from any ſort of people: for ſeveral ſorts of people are ſeveral wayes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, and will deſire liberty to give what they give in this kind, to ſuch as they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>and moſt affected to, whether Epiſcopal, Presbyterians, Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, or any others, and this liberty they ſhould have, and not be abridg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of it.</p>
            <p>But when I propoſe it to you to take care to contribute to the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Godly Miniſters, I mean (as I ſaid before) that you do herein but as your duty is to do, being private Chriſtians, <hi>viz.</hi> to contribute bountiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of your own eſtates; and the publick treaſury being in your hands, to diſpoſe a part thereof to this publick good work, but by no means (as I ſaid before) by vertue of your authority, to impoſe any thing upon the conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of particular people.</p>
            <p>And thus by inviting thoſe that now preach onely in private to their Churches, to preach in publick, and incouraging and deſiring men of eſtates to preach the Goſpel freely, and by reducing two or three Pariſhes into one, and aboliſhing tithes, and ſilencing idle dreans, and making proviſion for the maintenance of thoſe Goſpel-Preachers that have not eſtates out of the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſity lands and otherwiſe, you will do that which may very much tend to the propagation of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <note place="margin">6. Prop. That the poor be ſeriouſly conſidered of, and ſpeedily provided for, being a work the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires ſpecial care ſhould be taken of it.</note>6. That you ſeriouſly and in good earneſt lay to heart the condition of the poor, and make it your care to provide for the ſupply of their wants, and that conſideration be had of their Condition before any rich mans caſe what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever be taken into conſideration, how neerly ſo ever related to you, or any of you, (for I hope you will lay aſide your ſelves and your relations, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard them rather leſſe than more than others) for certainly the crying of the poor, and the ſighing of the needy, maketh a louder noiſe in the ears of the Lord of Sabbath, than the complaints of any rich man whatſoever; and his ear is more open to their cryes, and why ſhould not yours? Thoſe paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages <hi>Deut.</hi> 24. from the 10. V. to the end of the Chapter, wherein there are ſeveral Laws made by God, in which he maketh proviſion for the poor and needy, have taken great impreſſion upon my heart, eſpecially conſidering that it is he that requires his people to do ſo and ſo in the behalf of the diſtreſſed, and tells his people, that when they are compaſſionate, and ſhew acts of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and goodneſſe towards the poor, that he will bleſſe them for it in all the work of their hands, V. 19. and that it ſhall be righteouſneſſe unto them before the Lord their God, V. 13. which paſſages are worthy the ſerious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of every Saint, and eſpecially of thoſe that have moſt power to help the poor, as your Honours have; for certainly this great duty of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, and bowels of mercy and tenderneſſe, and doing good to the diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:153509:6"/>and needy, is more ſtrongly and eminently preſt in the Goſpel, than in the Law: but O how little is it practiſed (not to ſay in general in all Nations, but particularly) in <hi>England!</hi> it being a great ſcandal to religion in general, and a diſhonor to the Nation alſo, that ſo many beggars go up and down in all parts of this Nation as there do, ſome whereof may do it for neceſſity, becauſe they cannot otherwiſe live, though moſt do it out of idleneſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they will not work: wherfore if this courſe were taken, that every one that goeth up and down begging were taken, and preſently carried to ſome work-houſe, where they might be made to work, and allowed but ſome ſhort al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance for their work, it would make them that are able to work to refrain going a begging, and to ſet themſelves to ſome work or other whereby they might get more than poſſibly they may have at ſuch a work-houſe. And for ſuch as are poor, and withall known to be weak and ſickly, and unable to work, or have more children than their labour can afford bread for, it is a ſad thing, that among ſuch as profeſſe themſelves to be Saints, they ſhould be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to want bread. It is true; the Churches do make proviſion for all their poor, but muſt none but thoſe that are of Churches be provided for? as there are many godly people that are not in Church-fellowſhip, ſo there may be many goodly poor alſo that are not in Church fellowſhip, which ſhould be provided for, and not onely they, but others alſo, for we are to do good unto all, though eſpecially to thoſe who are of the houſhold of ſaith; and for this end it were neceſſary that ſome way were found out for the ſetting of all poor people a work, even ſuch as do not beg (but will neer ſtarve rather) but yet do want work, which they would willingly ſet themſelves unto, if they had but work to do, and then for others that cannot work, ſome waies ſhould be found out for their ſupplies, and this might be one way.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">That the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of letters may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted to the uſe of the poor.</note>That on the portage of all inland letters a price ſhould be fixed at 3d a let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or as your Honours ſhall think fit, and that ſome faithfull men be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed to mannage that buſineſs, who ſhould be allowed ſuch a certain ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend, for ſuch an imployment, and true accounts ſhould be kept of what is received weekly for letters, and what is disburſt quarterly or otherwiſe for the paying of ſuch as are imployed in ſeveral places, about the carrying up and down of letters, and the remainder ſhould come in for the uſe of the poor. And this being a publick thing, the benefit of it ſhould not go into any pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate mens purſes, and none of thoſe that are imployed about it ſhould have more than they deſerve for their pains, and time ſpent about doing the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs that concerns it, and ſo ſome thouſands of pounds might come in yearly to the poor that way.</p>
            <p>Another way might be that a ſeal might be made in every City, Town, and County, wherewith every conſiderable contract, bargain or agreement, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween man and man, ſhould be ſealed, for the Ratification of it, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which it ſhould be of no force, for which ſeal 6d. ſhould be given which might be of great uſe to the publick, and bring in an inſenſible income, for the uſe of the poor, faithfull men being appointed to be thoſe Seal-keepers, and to regiſter all perſons names, by whom ſuch bargains are made, and ſealed, and the time when.</p>
            <p>Other waies your Honours may alſo find out for the ſupply of the poor, as you ſee occaſion.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:153509:7"/>
               <note place="margin">7. Propoſal. That the meaner ſort of people may have as much or more favour ſhewn them in Courts of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice or other wiſe than the richeſt ſort.</note>7. Prop. That you having firſt provided for the very pooreſt ſort, then next that you conſider the conditions of ſuch as are next them and are in a mean condition, though not in ſo mean a condition as to want bread, and to ſtand in need of almes. And the conſideration you are to have of their condition, is to provide that if they be wronged or defrauded by any, that you do them right, or appoint ſome to do them right, before you do ſuch acts of juſtice for perſons of greater eſtates.</p>
            <p>The ground of this propoſall is, becauſe it is ordinarily ſo carried, that the rich mans cauſe is heard before the poors; but O do you extraordinary things and let not ſuch corruptions be in your proceedings! and according to the peoples poverty or meaneſs, wealth or riches, let care be taken for their relief, wherein they are wronged, and let the richeſt of all be relieved laſt of all, becauſe that ordinarily they have had relief firſt formerly: But if this reaſon be not ſufficient then this is, Becauſe the richeſt are better able to bear delaies than meaner people are. But it is ſad to conſider how contrary to this rule things have been formerly carried. As for inſtance, ſeveral ſorts of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple did contribute out of their eſtates in money and plate for the defence of the late Parliament, and the richeſt were firſt paid, for they having money by them did double what was due to them, and had all their disburſements in lands, in which many of them had ſuch good penyworths as it was bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to them than ready money: But the poor that had not to double it, they could not have their money to this day, only there was an Act that all whoſe debts were under ten pound, ſhould be ſatisfyed, by vertue of which Act, there were indeed a ſmall number of poor people whoſe debts were ſatisfied. But alas there were many godly poor people that were ſo zealous for that good cauſe that then was proſecuted; that they disburſt, ſome above ten, others above twenty, thirty, fifty pounds for the Parliament, that it now may be, by reaſon of the warrs, and of their great ſufferings, have far leſs eſtates than many covetous perſons that lent but 5 or 10. l. ſo that ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction ſhould be made unto perſons, ſooner or later, not according to the ſum they disburſt, but according to the preſent condition of meaneſs, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities in which they are.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <note place="margin">8. Propoſal. That Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſioners be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to diſpatch all buſineſſes and redreſs all grievances of people in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſpective Counties where they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ve.]</note>8. Prop. That a certain number of perſons be authorized by you to ſit as Commiſſioners in every County, to hear the grievances of people, and to diſpatch all buſineſs for them, that they be not inforced to come to <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> for every occaſion, as they have hitherto done, and yet do (which is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding chargeable to all, but eſpecially to thoſe that live in remote parts) to wait upon Commiſſioners here 3 moneths, 6 moneths, and ſometimes 12 moneths together, but that thoſe people may have their buſineſs done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a daies walk of their own habitations, as it may very well be in ſome lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Counties, if the Commiſſioners do ſit in the moſt commodious place for ſituation in ſuch Counties, not ſo much aiming at the bigneſs, or largeneſſe, of ſuch a Town or village, as the Situation of it, and in other Counties that are larger, there may be Commiſſioners appointed to ſit in two, or three ſeveral places in thoſe Counties, according to the largeneſs of them, that ſo it may be as eaſie for them to diſpatch buſineſſe, as for thoſe that are in leſſe Counties; and buſineſs might be thus carried on with leſſe charge to the Commonwealth in general, and be leſſe burt henſome to the particular mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:153509:7"/>of it, than now it is, As for inſtance, The Commiſſioners for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding, and the Commiſſioners for removing Obſtructions, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners for ſale of Lands, do all ſit here, and all that have any buſineſs in either of theſe caſes, muſt attend them here, though they live as far as <hi>Cornwall</hi> and <hi>York ſhire,</hi> and here wait ſeveral moneths before their buſineſs can be diſpatched, whereas were there Commiſſioners authorized to fit in every County, to diſpatch the ſame buſineſſes, The rules which are preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to theſe here to proceed by, would alſo ſerve for all the Commiſſioners in every County, and buſineſs might be far better carried on; for they ſitting in every County, would be better enabled to take cognizance of every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular mans caſe, than theſe here can; for here they take the oaths of they know not whom, and acording to thoſe oaths whether true or falſe they paſs the buſineſs; whereas in each particular County they might have more cleer knowledge what the perſons are that ſwear to ſuch or ſuch a thing, and be able to judge of what credit their oathes are, which here they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not do: and then for the worth and value of Lands, they might be beter, and more fully informed than theſe Commiſſioners here can; for they truſt to their Surveyors, and theſe Surveyors may be and ſometimes are bribed, and lands are and have been undervalued, to the great prejudice of the Common-wealth. In theſe and ſeverall other reſpects, great inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces come, for want of Commiſſioners ſitting in every County, for the relief of the people, and the righting of the Commonwealth.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <note place="margin">9. Propoſal. That all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable and ſtriſ-increaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance-devour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing laws, and Lawiers be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed and abandoned.</note>9. Prop. That you do wholly aboliſh and repeal thoſe great and tedious volumes of Law, that are either in a ſtrange tongue or otherwiſe (which ſerve for no other end, but to enrich the Lawyers, and impoveriſh others) and prepare inſtead thereof only ſome plain brief generall rules, which all men may be acquainted with, and appoint onely ſuch pious, faithful and diſcreet men, for the adminiſtration of Juſtice, as never knew what thoſe old laws meant, leaving them to do in matters of juſtice what the Law of God, and nature guides them to; very much whereof is contained in this, that men do as they would be done unto: for the happineſſe of a people will never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in good lawes, but in good Magiſtrates, or adminiſtrators of Juſtice, and you need not fear to aboliſh thoſe old ambiguous, ſtrife-increaſing, and ſubſtance devouring laws, for fear that you ſhall not find men enough fit, and able to judge with more righteous Judgement, then thoſe lawes of themſelves can guide them to; for bleſſed be the great God he hath poured out his ſpirit upon many already, and without all diſpute, he will pour out of that ſpirit of his more and more, upon his people in theſe our daies; for the Kingdome and appearing of Jeſus Chriſt, is now near at hand, it is even at the door<note n="*" place="margin">My ground for this are laid down a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> large in my Book entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>New Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalems Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi>
               </note>, and be you ſtrong and of good courage, and do his work, and your Lord when he cometh will bleſſe and reward you, if he find you ſo doing.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <note place="margin">10. Propoſal. That none be henceforth conſtituted Juſtice of the Peace or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrators of Juſtice but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uch as are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en fearing God and hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</note>10. Prop. That you pick out the choiceſt men in each County for holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of life, and freedome from covetouſneſſe, and for wiſdome, prudence and underſtanding, whether rich men, or mean men, for the mannaging of your waightieſt buſineſs, as to be Commiſſioners, and doers of juſtice between man and man, &amp; put down theſe old cuſtomes, of making the rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt men of the places where they live, Aldermen, and Juſtices of the Peace,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:153509:8"/>though they be very Dunces, and very profane in their lives, who cannot chaſtiſe ſwearers and blaſphemers, becauſe they are ſuch themſelves, nor drunkards, becauſe it is a vice they are guilty of themſelves; the like may be ſaid of other vices; but let it be your ſpecial care that faithfull and diſcreet men be appointed to adminiſter juſtice throughout the Nation; and then for other imployments, as the Cuſtom offices, and the like, if there be not godly men enough to be found for them, they may be diſpoſed of to others, that are of moſt civil and blameleſſe converſation; but if Godly and conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious men may be found for all, then ſuch ſhould be choſen before others, and things ſhould not be carryed as they have lately been, that enemies and men of vicious lives ſhould be imployed, when honeſt and faithful men that have ſuffered much for their faithfulneſſe to the Common wealth, could never yet be imployed, becauſe they had not ſo many friends to ſpeak for them, nor did not ſo eagerly ſeek after places as others did.</p>
            <p n="11">
               <note place="margin">11. Prop. That no offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer that ſerves the Common wealth in ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mployments as are not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ardous to their lives or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ealths be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>owed more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>han 200 l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er annum.</note>11. Prop. That moderate and reaſonable ſtipends, be allowed unto all thoſe that are imployed, that they may have no temptation to do the work grudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, or ſparingly, but may dilligently attend it, as they ought to do, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided it be no ſuch ſtipend as may enrich men, but that it may be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a diſhonourable thing for to have it ſaid that ſuch a man was but in a mean condition the other day, and now is enricht by the publick treaſure, I mean for ſuch men as live at home and in eaſe, and do not at all hazard their lives, or health, or limbs, for the publick welfare; but as for ſuch as ſo do, it would be ingratitude in a high degree, if they were not well rewarded; but it is no ingratitude to give thoſe men but mean rewards, that do but mean a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d eaſy ſervices; for to be Commiſſioner of the Cuſtoms is eaſie ſervice, and to be a Treaſurer or the like, is eaſie ſervice, and ordinary rewards may ſuffice for them, ſo that no man for the diſcharge of ſuch offices, ſhould have more than 150 l. or 200 l. <hi>per annum,</hi> even they that have moſt, and are in the moſt honourable of ſuch imployments, and others but 40.50.60. or 100 l. <hi>per an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> according to the quality ſuch perſons have lived in, and the imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they ſhall be fit for: for ſome men of mean parts, may be fit onely for mean imployments; whereas other imployments require men of better parts, learning and abilities for the mannaging of them, and ſuch men as have been ſo brought up, and are ſo quallified, will deſerve greater ſtipends anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thereunto; but any man though he hath five or ſix children, may main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain his family very comfortably with 200 a year, though not in outward ſtate and pomp, and needleſſe vanities, in maintaining muſick and dancing-Maſters to teach their children, and decking of them in ſilks and ſilver, and the like; men that have eſtates of their own before, may do in theſe things what they pleaſe, but it ſhould never be ſaid that the publick treaſure ſhould be ſo expended, for there are many other more neceſſary things to be done there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, and not to beſtow a thouſand, or five hundred, or three hundred a year either, upon any man that is imployed in eaſy and peaceable imployments at home.</p>
            <p>And ſome Gentlemen of noble and publick ſpirits, who are men of great gifts for underſtanding and prudence, and have withall a holy heart, and zealous for God, who have great eſtates of their own, will be found no doubt ready and free whenſoever they ſhall be deſired to officiate in Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:153509:8"/>imployments (as in being adminiſtrators of juſtice and Commiſſioners in other caſes, &amp;c.) and will not take any reward at all for it, but do it out of deſire to be doing ſervice for Chriſt, and to be improving their Talents for his uſe, but will be unwilling that ever it ſhould be ſaid that they were made rich by the Common-wealths Treaſure, (as to the Honour of many no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Gentlemen in the Land, it may be yet ſaid of them they have not medled with it) even ſuch as <hi>Abraham</hi> as would not take of the King of <hi>Sodom</hi> the worth of a thread even to a ſhoe latchet, leſt it ſhould be ſaid he had made <hi>Abraham</hi> rich. But other men of mean eſtates being men of large abilities, and of great Wiſdom and Prudence, and Piety, being imployed in ſuch of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices (for want of rich men enough ſo qualified) ſhould be allowed as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p n="12">
               <note place="margin">12. Prop. That no more of the lands belon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth be henceforth ſold, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the people Taxes &amp; Ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciſe &amp; cuſtom</note>12. Prov. That you ſell no more of thoſe Lands that are forfeited to the Common-wealth, either in <hi>England, Scotland</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> than of meer neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity you muſt, at the leaſt that you do not ſell them wholly, but ſell them one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for ſeven or ten years time, that ſo afterward they may come into the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick cuſtody again, and ſerve to defray publick charges, that ſo taxes, exciſe, and cuſtomes, thoſe great burdens of the people may be taken off.</p>
            <p>And thus I leave theſe few Propoſals to your Honours ſerious-conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, having great expectations that the Lord will make of you repayers of breaches and reſtorers of paths to dwell in.</p>
            <p>And that to this end he will powre out his Spirit upon you, even the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Wiſdome, and Underſtanding, the Spirit of Counſel and Might, and the Spirit of Knowledge, and of the Fear of the Lord, that ſo you may be of quick underſtanding in the fear of the Lord, and may judge with Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe the poor, and reprove with equity for the meek of the Earth<note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 11.2.</note>, as it is ſaid your Lord and Maſter Jeſus Chriſt ſhall do when he cometh, is the fervent prayer of.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>The unworthy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of Chriſt and his people,</hi> M. R.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>July</hi> 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1653.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
